John Mayfield Collection Relating to Eugene O'Neill
John Mayfield Collection Relating to Eugene O'Neill
1924-1961
Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983.
0.5 linear ft.
Most of the collection relates to John S. Mayfield's, "Eugene O'Neill and the Senator from Texas." Collection contains correspondence between Mayfield and others such as Carlotta O'Neill and O'Neill biographer Louis Sheaffer. Also in the collection are manuscripts, drafts and proofs of Mayfield's work, and printed material about O'Neill.
3263480
Biographical History
Eugene O'Neill (1888-1953) was an American dramatist and winner of the 1936 Nobel Prize for Literature. Among his best-known works are Desire Under the Elms, Mourning Becomes Electra, and the semi-autobiographical Long Day's Journey Into Night.
Earle B. Mayfield (1881-1964) was an American attorney and United States Senator from Texas. John S. Mayfield, American bibliographer and book collector, was his son.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Mayfield Collection Relating to Eugene O'Neill consists of correspondence, printed material and writings.
Correspondence consists primarily of correspondence between Mayfield and others relating to his publication of five letters from O'Neill to Mayfield's father, Texas senator Earle B. Mayfield. Photostats of the letters are included in the collection. There is also correspondence between John Mayfield and O'Neill's widow, Carlotta O'Neill. Other correspondents include O'Neill biographer Louis Sheaffer and Earle B. Mayfield.
Printed material consists of newspaper clippings about O'Neill on the occasion of his death and one about his wife Carlotta's death, and a variety of items such as a cartoon, a program for a production of Long Day's Journey Into Night, and so on.
Writings contains drafts, proofs and final published versions of Mayfield's "Eugene O'Neill and the Senator from Texas," and one copy of Mayfield's "Black Badge of Treason" (about Ezra Pound).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. The other series are in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Literature -- American Fiction; Mayfield, Earle Bradford, 1881-1964.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Black badge of treason.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Eugene O'Neill and the senator from Texas.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Eugene O'Neill and the senator from Texas.; O'Neill, Carlotta.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953 -- History and criticism.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972 -- History and criticism.; Sheaffer, Louis.; Dramatists, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Page proofs.; Programs (documents); Biographers.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John S. Mayfield.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - O'Neill, Carlotta, 1960-1961; includes letters written on her behalf by her agent, Jane Rubin (Box 1)
  - O'Neill, Eugene, 1924; 1925; photostats of letters to Earle B. Mayfield (Box 1)
  - Others, 1951-1952; 1956-1961,; undated; includes Earle B. Mayfied and Louis Sheaffer (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Newspaper clippings, 1953; undated; most are obituaries or other announcements of O'Neill's death, also one about his wife (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946; 1954,; 1956,; 1957; cartoon, program from an O'Neill play, article in Newsweek, etc. (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Black Badge of Treason, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Eugene O'Neill and the Senator from Texas, 1961
    - Drafts (Box 1)
    - Proofs (Box 1)
    - Final published version (Box 1)